<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>PIOTR BENTKOWSKI, PhD</title>
 <link href="https://bentkowski.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://bentkowski.net/"/>
 <updated>2025-01-05T22:02:42+01:00</updated>
 <id>https://bentkowski.net</id>
 <author>
   <name>Piotr Bentkowski</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>All the different ways and reasons your papers get cited in the scientific literature</title>
   <link href="https://bentkowski.net/2020/02/29/different-ways-of-getting-cited/"/>
   <updated>2020-02-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://bentkowski.net/2020/02/29/different-ways-of-getting-cited</id>
   <content type="html">Few words about the most important aspect of the modern scientific folklore - Citing. And how it is done. Not too serious.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Our paper showing that the sexual selection can both inflate or deflate MHC gene number is in the wild!</title>
   <link href="https://bentkowski.net/2020/02/26/prsb-paper-out/"/>
   <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://bentkowski.net/2020/02/26/prsb-paper-out</id>
   <content type="html">We have gotten published! Jacek Radwan and I published a paper titled &quot;Mating preferences can drive expansion or contraction of major histocompatibility complex gene family&quot; for which I created agent-based model simulations.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Our paper investigating how pathogen richness, the cost of expressing MHC variants, and pathogens' mutation rate shape the individual MHC copy number is out!</title>
   <link href="https://bentkowski.net/2019/05/17/PLoS-Comp-Biol-paper-out-MHC-evolution/"/>
   <updated>2019-05-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://bentkowski.net/2019/05/17/PLoS-Comp-Biol-paper-out-MHC-evolution</id>
   <content type="html">We have gotten published! Jacek Radwan and I published a paper titled &quot;Evolution of major histocompatibility complex gene copy number&quot;. It&apos;s a theoretical study using agent-based simulation I&apos;d coded addressing the question how parasite diversity, their speed of evolution and costs of expressing MHC proteins shape the MHC genes&apos; individual copy number variation in hosts.</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Naukowy exodus</title>
   <link href="https://bentkowski.net/2017/09/28/naukowy-exodus/"/>
   <updated>2017-09-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://bentkowski.net/2017/09/28/naukowy-exodus</id>
   <content type="html">Czas powiedzieć to głośno - jeszcze chwila dalszych zaniedbań i pozostaniemy bez naukowców. Trwa odpływ naukowców średniego szczebla kariery</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Granty ERC a sprawa polska, czyli uczony głodny jest o wiele mniej płodny</title>
   <link href="https://bentkowski.net/2017/09/27/uczony_glodny/"/>
   <updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://bentkowski.net/2017/09/27/uczony_glodny</id>
   <content type="html">Polskie instytucje naukowe są za biedne, aby skutecznie konkurować o granty Europejskiej Rady ds. Badań Naukowych. Mamy ich tyle, ile wynika z naszych wydatków na badania i rozwój (analiza AD 2016)</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
